

Expertise:

Lean & Kanban Agile / Scrum eXtreme Programming (XP) Facilitation Mediation Unit Testing Human Systems Dynamics Story Mapping Enterprise Architecture

Languages/Frameworks:

Ruby, Rails, JavaScript, React, Redux, Clojure, NodeJS, C#, Objective-C, Java

Education:

University of Southern California BS in Computer Science

jeremy.lightsmith@gmail.com http://jeremylightsmith.com/ linked in

10100 4th Ave NW Seattle, WA 98177

312-953-1193 (cell)

JEREMY LIGHTSMITH

Executive Summary

A seasoned agile coach, trainer & facilitator, Jeremy has spent the last 20+ years managing, organizing, and building software products and teams

Jeremy excels at creating environments where teams can discover how they work best. He is a committed teacher with a deep understanding of agile, and is constantly looking for better ways to share knowledge and collaborate.

Jeremy has spent most of his career working on and toward agile & lean teams in quickly changing environments. He has a solid track record of driving projects to successful release and a wide range of experience across many industries to pull from.

Experience

Transparent Classroom, 2012 - present

FOUNDER / CEC

I grew this from a project I hacked on nights and weekends to a team of 9 that serves 100K children in 1200 Montessori schools across 65 countries with 1M+ revenue. We are the industry leader for Montessori school record keeping, and have been profitable for 5 years.

Outpace Systems, Inc, 2014 - 2016

TEAM LEAD / SOFTWARE DEVELOPER

I led one of the most important projects at Outpace. While I spent most of my time here writing code, my more unique contributions include: setting meeting protocols company wide, facilitating our bi-annual Open Space conference, introducing better processes and tools for managing work.

Lightsmith Consulting LLC, 2009 - 2014

AGILE COACH / TRAINER / FACILITATOR

I worked with & coached teams that want to be more lean & agile. My engagements ranged from an afternoon training to multi-year embedded coaching and delivery.

COACH / DEVELOPER (RUBY/JS), Client: Nordstrom Innovation Lab

Founding member of the lab. I helped build the team and shape the process Nordstrom uses for innovation. For several years, I led the team through exploring scores of ideas and adopting Lean Startup, Design Thinking, and more.

AGILE COACH (.NET), Client: Vertafore, Insurance Company

Helped their 40 developer team through their third year of agile adoption. I introduced dev practices, coached scrum masters, led workshops.

AGILE COACH / ADVISOR, Client: Kiha, Startup

As Kiha grows, they brought me in periodically to give them feedback and guidance on their process.

INSTRUCTOR (RUBY/OBJC), Client: Startup Weekend

I designed & taught intensive Rails & iOS courses for Startup Weekend before bootcamps were cool :).

INSTRUCTOR (RUBY), Client: University of Washington

I designed & taught a 10 week Ruby on Rails course.

SENIOR DEVELOPER, Client: SerialsSolutions

I worked on Rails frontend for a next generation library search service.

Barking Minds, 2010 - 2012

FOUNDER / PRODUCT OWNER / DEVELOPER (RUBY/JS/OBJC)

I created Barking Minds for freelancers to come together to create beautiful software. I led our small team to build a mindmapping tool that worked across Web & iOS.

Pivotal Labs, 2007 - 2009

Pivotal provides on-demand project teams for well funded startups. As an "Anchor", I led teams, managed scope and customers. I also introduced Agile Inceptions, which they continued after I left.

CLIENT PRINCIPAL / LEAD (RUBY), Client: Knowledge Management Company

I led inception to launch in 4 months. Twelve person team delivered site capable of serving terabytes of information to web & mobile apps.

ARCHITECT / SENIOR DEVELOPER (RUBY), Client: Custom Book Publishing Company

Concept to launch in 3 months. I implemented much of frontend and backend, capable of supporting thousands of concurrent users, ordering, customizing, and printing books.

CLIENT PRINCIPAL / LEAD (RUBY), Client: Major Construction Company

I led punchlist product from inception to launch. Requirements included handling millions of records, concurrent users and offline access. We delivered on time and budget

CLIENT PRINCIPAL / LEAD (RUBY), Client: Construction Services Company

My 6 person team did a rewrite of their flagship product from Java to Rails in 6 months.

SENIOR DEVELOPER, <u>Product: Pivotal Tracker</u>

As a senior developer, I worked on a UI overhaul as we pushed it toward full public release.

ThoughtWorks Inc., 2000-2007

I served as a coach, developer, and facilitator to many projects during my tenure. I learned a ton and even got a chance to pair with people like Ward Cunningham, Martin Fowler, Robert Martin, and Brian Marick.

LEAD FACILITATOR / TRAINER, QuickStart Engagements

Started several small to multi-million projects with inceptions and trained other facilitators to give them.

DEV LEAD / PRODUCT OWNER (RUBY), Product: CruiseControl.rb

Led team to deliver 1.0 ruby version of Cruise Control. Became standard CI solution for many years.

PRODUCT CONSULTANT (.NET), Client: Language Workbench Product Company

Drove requirements and served as industry expert for next generation Domain Specific Language IDE.

AGILE COACH / SENIOR ARCHITECT (.NET), Client: Major Financial Company

Helped 30 person team adopt agile across 3 site and pioneered .NET architecture in the early days.

SENIOR DEVELOPER / TEAM LEAD (JAVA), Client: Major Petroleum Company

I helped set methodology / architecture on 100+ person project, and migrated data from 100+ legacy tables.

AGILE COACH / DEV LEAD (JAVA), Client: Container Shipping Web Service

I introduced XP to the client and pioneered n-stage XSLT for generating HTML.

IBM Corp. (C++), 1999-2000

SOFTWARE DEVELOPER / TEAM LEAD

I led the Windows GUI team on a large-scale cross-platform C++/Java environment.

Other Relevant Professional & Community Experience

Retreat of TBD 2018-present

FOUNDER / OPEN SPACE FACILITATOR

Human Systems Dynamics Institute 2018-2020

BOARD MEMBER

Chautauqua Retreat 2012-2017

FOUNDER / OPEN SPACE FACILITATOR

I started this bi-annual retreat as a way for awesome people to share and learn from each other. I did facilitation for it and led the community through conflict when it came up.

Lighthouse Montessori School 2008-present

FOUNDER / BOARD CHAIR

I co-founded this one classroom Montessori school for 3-6 year olds and continue to serve as chair.

Burn Blue 2007-2013

FOUNDER / DIRECTOR

Founded this non-profit to host blues dancing in Seattle. My contributions were its focus on community involvement & growth. We grew to 200 people a night and made it profitable for organizers, teachers and DJs.

Marathon 2002-2003

FOUNDER / PRODUCT MANAGER / DEVELOPER (JAVA/SWING)

Started this open source project to provide testing for java swing.

Blues Dance 2005-2009 ORGANIZER / TEACHER

I organized national dance events and taught at local and national levels.

References available upon request